<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info"
     docName="draft-gcdrb-teas-5g-network-slice-application-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="draft-gcdrb-teas-5g-network-slice-application-00">IETF
    Network Slice Application in 5G End-to-End Network Slice</title>

    <author fullname="Xuesong Geng" initials="X." surname="Geng">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <email>gengxuesong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Luis M. Contreras" initials="L." surname="Contreras">
      <organization>Telefonica</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>luismiguel.contrerasmurillo@telefonica.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Reza Rokui" initials="R." surname="Rokui">
      <organization>Ciena</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>rrokui@ciena.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jie Dong" initials="J." surname="Dong">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <email>jie.dong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ivan Bykov" initials="I." surname="Bykov">
      <organization>Ribbon Communications</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>Ivan.Bykov@rbbn.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="21" month="September" year="2022"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>TEAS Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Sample</keyword>

    <keyword>Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Network Slicing is one of the core features in 5G, which provides
      different network service as independent logical networks. To provide 5G
      network slices service, an end-to-end network slice needs to consists of
      3 major types of network segments: Radio Access Network (RAN), Mobile
      Core Network (CN) and Transport Network (TN). This document describes
      the application of IETF network slice in providing 5G end-to-end network
      slices, including the network slice identification mapping, network
      slice parameter mapping and 5G IETF Network Slice NBI.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t/>

      <t>Driven by the new applications of 5G, the concept of network slicing
      is defined to provide a logical network with specific capabilities and
      characteristics. Network slice contains a set of network functions and
      allocated resources(e.g. computation, storage and network
      resources).</t>

      <t>The IETF Network Slice (NS) service is defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slices"/> as a set of connections
      between a number of CEs, with that connections having specific Service
      Level Objectives (SLOs) and Service Level Expectations (SLEs) over a
      common underlay network, with the traffic of one customer being
      separated from another. The concept of IETF network slice is conceived
      as technology agnostic.</t>

      <t>The IETF NS service is specified in terms of the set of endpoints
      (from CE perspective) connected to the slice, the type of connectivity
      among them, and a set of SLOs and SLEs for each connectivity
      construct.</t>

      <t>In <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slice-nbi-yang"/>, the
      endpoints are described by an identifier, with some metrics associated
      to the connections among them as well as certain policies (e.g., rate
      limits for incoming and outgoing traffic).</t>

      <t>The 5G network slice as defined in [3GPP TS 23.501] does not take the
      transport network slice into consideration. This document introduces the
      concept of 5G end-to-end network slice, which is composed of three major
      types network segments: Radio Access Network (RAN), Transport Network
      (TN) and Mobile Core Network (CN). Transport network is supposed to
      provide the required connectivity between AN and CN or inside AN/CN,
      with specific performance commitment. For each end-to-end network slice,
      the topology and performance requirement for transport network can be
      very different, which requests transport network to have the capability
      of supporting multiple different transport network slices.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminologies">
      <t/>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in [RFC2119].</t>

      <t>Terminologies for IETF Network Slice go along with the definition in
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slices"/>.</t>

      <t>The following terms are used in this document:</t>

      <t>NSC: IETF Network Slice Controller</t>

      <t>NSI: Network Slice Instance</t>

      <t>NSSI: Network Slice Subnet Instance</t>

      <t>S-NSSAI: Single Network Slice Selection Assistance Information</t>

      <t>RAN: Radio Access Network</t>

      <t>TN: Transport Network</t>

      <t>CN: Mobile Core Network</t>

      <t>DSCP: Differentiated Services Code Point</t>

      <t>CSMF: Communication Service Management Function</t>

      <t>NSMF: Network Slice Management Function</t>

      <t>NSSMF: Network Slice Subnet Management Function</t>
    </section>

    <section title="5G End-to-End Network Slice">
      <t>The scope of 5G End-to-End Network Slice discussed in this document
      is shown in figure 1. Transport network provides connectivity between
      and inside RAN and CN. To support fully automated enablement and
      assurance of 5G E2E network slices, multiple controllers are needed to
      manage 5G E2E network slices in RAN, Core and Transport domains. In
      addition, an E2E network slice orchestrator is needed to provide
      coordination and control of network slices from an E2E perspective.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[  
       +-----------------------------------------------------+
       |          +-----------------------------+            |            
 |-----+----------+----------------+            |            | 
 |   ******   +---+---+   ******   | +----+     |            |  
 |  *      *  |       |  *      *  | |    |     |            | 
 | *  RAN   ---  TN   ---  RAN   --|--    |     |            |  
 |  * NFs  *  |       |  * NFs  *  | |    |     |            |  
 |   ******   +-------+   ******   | |    |     |            |
 |---------------------------------+ |    |   +-+--+  +------+------+
                 RAN                 |    |   |IETF|  |   5G E2E    |
                                     |    +---+ NSC+--+Network Slice|
                                     |TN  |   |    |  | Orchestrator|
                                     |    |   +-+--+  +------+------+
 +---------------------------------+ |    |     |            |           
 |   ******   +-------+   ******   | |    |     |            |        
 |  *      *  |       |  *      *  | |    |     |            |        
 | *  CN    ---  TN   ---  CN   ---|--    |     |            |           
 |  * NFs  *  |       |  * NFs  *  | |    |     |            |           
 |   ******   +---+---+   ******   | +----+     |            |           
 +-----+----------+----------------+            |            |          
       |        CN|                             |            |  
       |          +-----------------------------+            |  
       +-----------------------------------------------------+
        Figure-1 Scope of 5G End to End Network Slice
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Depend on the RAN technology deployment, the 5G IETF network slices
      are sets of connections between network functions and mobile
      applications:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>IETF Network Slices in Distributed RAN deployment</t>
        </list>Distributed RAN is the most common deployment of 4G and 5G RAN
      networks as shown in Figure 2-1. The RAN network is connected to Core
      network (CN) using the IETF transport network (TN).</t>

      <t>In this case, a single E2E network slice contains not only RAN and
      Core slices but IETF network slices INS_1 which provides the
      connectivity between RAN to CN slices.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   <-------- 5G E2E Network Slice  -------->
   <--- RS ------->                <-- CS -->
                    <--- INS_1 -->           
   ..................
   : RAN            :
   :                : .............           
   :                : :           : |------|  
   :                : :    TN     : | CN   |  
   :                : :           : |------|  
   :                : :...........:           
   :................:

   Legend
     INS: IETF Network Slice
     RS: RAN Slice
     CS: Core Slice
     TN: IETF network

      Figure 2-1:  IETF network slices in distributed RAN deployment]]></artwork>
        </figure><list style="symbols">
          <t>IETF Network Slices in Centralized RAN deployment</t>
        </list>The RAN consists of two functional units: the baseband unit and
      the radio unit (RU). The baseband unit processes the radio signal and is
      connected to the transport network. The RU transmits and receives the
      carrier signal that is transmitted over the air to the end user
      equipment (UE). In Centralized RAN as depicted in Figure 2-2, the RU and
      baseband are separated by a network called fronthaul network.</t>

      <t>In this deployment a single 5G E2E network slice contains not only 5G
      RAN and 5G Core slices but one IETF network slice INS_1 where INS_1 is
      identical to their counterparts in distributed RAN deployment case.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[ <--------------- 5G E2E Network Slice ---------->
 <-------- RS -------->                 <-- CS -->
                         <--- INS_1 --->          
...........................
:  RAN                    :
:        ........         : .............          
: |----| :      : |-----| : :           : |------| 
: | RU | :  FN  : |     | : :    TN     : | CN   | 
: |----| :      : |-----| : :           : |------| 
:        :......:         : :...........:          
:.........................:

Legend
  INS: IETF Network Slice
  RS: RAN Slice
  CS: Core Slice
  FN: Fronthaul IETF network
  TN: IETF network
  RU: Radio Unit

     Figure 2-2:  IETF network slices in Centralized RAN deployment]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>5G IETF Network Slices in Cloud RAN (C-RAN)</t>
        </list>In Cloud-RAN deployment, the baseband unit is further
      disaggregated into real-time and non-real-time components. The former is
      deployed close to antenna to manages the real-time air interface
      resources while the non-real-time control functions are hosted centrally
      in the cloud. These components are called CU (Central Unit) and DU
      (Distributed Unit) as shown in Figure 2-3 where these entities are
      connected by a new network called Midhaul network.</t>

      <t>In this deployment a single E2E network slice contains not only RAN
      and 5G Core slices but IETF network slices INS_1 and INS_2 where INS_1
      is identical to their counterparts in centralized RAN deployment case
      (see Figure 2-2) and a new IETF network slice INS_2 connects the DUs to
      CUs through F1 interface.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[ <----------------- 5G E2E Network Slice  ---------------->
 <--------------- RS ------------>                 <- CS ->
                     <-- INS_2 -->     <-- INS_1 ->     
 ......................................
 :  RAN                               :
 :        ......        ......        : ........          
 :|----|  :    : |----| :    : |----| : :      : |------| 
 :| RU |  : FN : | DU | : MN : | CU | : :  TN  : | Core | 
 :|----|  :    : |----| :    : |----| : :      : |------| 
 :        :....:        :....:        : :......:          
 :                                    :
 :....................................:

Legend
  INS: IETF Network Slice
  RS: RAN Slice
  CS: Core Slice
  FN: Fronthaul IETF network
  MN: Midhaul IETF bnetwork
  TN: Backhaul IETF network
  DU: Distributed Unit
  CU: Central Unit
  RU: Radio Unit

         Figure 2-3: IETF network slices in Cloud RAN (C-RAN) deployment]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>For the sake of description, the descriptions below all take the TN
      slice between RAN and CN as an example, and the other cases are
      similar.</t>

      <t>The following figure shows the correspondence between network
      entities in E2E 5G slices and IETF slices respectively.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[     +---------------------+                                                    
     |         CSMF        |                                                    
     +----------|----------+                                                    
                |                    +------------------------+                 
     +---------------------+         |  5G E2E Network Slice  |                 
     |         NSMF        |         |      Orchestrator      |                 
     +---------------------+         +------------------------+                 
           /    |    \                            |                          
          /     |     \                  NSC NBI  |                          
         /      |      \                          |                          
+---------++---------++---------+    +------------------------+           
|    AN   ||    TN   ||   CN    |    |   IETF Network Slice   |                 
|   NSSMF ||   NSSMF ||  NSSMF  |    |     Controller (NSC)   |                 
|         ||         ||         |    +------------------------+                 
+---------++---------++---------+         NSC SBI |                          
     |          |          |                      |                          
     |          |          |         +------------------------+           
     |          |          |         |    Network Controllers |                 
     |          |          |         +------------------------+           
     |          |          |                      |                       
     |          |          |                      |                      
   ******      ******     ******               ******                        
  *  5G  *    * IETF *   *  5G  *             * IETF *                       
 *   RAN  *  * Network* *  Core  *           * Network*                      
  *      *    *      *   *      *             *      *                       
   ******      ******     ******               ******  

Figure-3 Correspondence between 5G E2E Slices and IETF Slices
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>An example of 5G E2E Network Slice is showed in figure 4. Each e2e
      network slice contains AN slice, CN slice and one or more IETF network
      Slices. 3GPP identifies each e2e network slice using an integer called
      S-NSSAI. In Figure 4 there are three instances of e2e network slices
      which are identified by S-NSSAI 01111111, 02222222 and 02333333,
      respectively. Each instance of e2e network slice contains AN slice, CN
      Slice and one or more IETF network slices. For example, e2e network
      slice 01111111 has AN Slice instance 4, CN Slice instance 1 and IETF
      network slice 6. Note that 3GPP does not cover the IETF network slice.
      See <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slices"/> for details of
      IETF network slice.</t>

      <t>Note that 3GPP uses the terms NSI and NSSI which are a set of network
      function and required resources (e.g. compute, storage and networking
      resources) which corresponds to network slice Instance, whereas S-NSSAI
      is an integer that identifies the e2e network slice.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[            +-----------+ +-----------+  +-----------+                    
            |  S-NSSAI  | |  S-NSSAI  |  |  S-NSSAI  |                    
            |  01111111 | |  02222222 |  |  03333333 |                    
            +---|-------+ +---|---|---+  +----|------+                    
                |  +----------+   |           |                              
                V  V              V           V
              *******       ********      ********                        
Core         * NSSI 1 *    * NSSI 2 *    * NSSI 3 *                       
Network       ********      ********      ********                        
                  \              \             /                          
                   \              \           /                           
                   +-----+       +-----+    +-----+                           
Transport          | IETF|       | IETF|    | IETF|
Network            | NS 6|       | NS 7|    | NS 8|                      
                   +-----+       +-----+    +-----+                         
                       \              \   /                               
                        \              \ /                                
  Radio                 ********     ********                             
 Access                * NSSI 4 *   * NSSI 5 *                            
 Network                ********     ******** 


Figure 4 5G End-to-End Network Slice and its components
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The following network slice related identifiers in management plane,
      control plane and data(user) plane play an important role in end-to- end
      network slice mapping:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Single Network Slice Selection Assistance Information(S-NSSAI):
          The end-to-end network slice identifier, which is defined in
          [TS23501]; S-NSSAI is used during 3GPP network slice signalling
          process.</t>

          <t>IETF Network Slice Identifier: An identifier allocated by IETF
          Neetwork Slice Controller (NSC) in management plane. In data plane,
          IETF Network Slice Identifier may be instantiated with existing data
          plane identifiers and doesn't necessarily require new
          encapsulation.</t>

          <t>IETF Network Slice Interworking Identifier: Data-plane network
          slice identifier which is used for mapping the end-to-end network
          slice traffic to specific IETF network slice. The IETF Network Slice
          Interworking Identifier is a new concept introduced by this draft,
          which may be instantiated with existing data plane identifiers and
          doesn't necessarily require new encapsulation.</t>
        </list>The relationship between these identifiers are specifies in the
      following sections.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="3GPP Network Slice Mapping Parameters">
      <t>The network slice concept was introduced in 3GPP specifications from
      the first 5G release, corresponding to Release 15. As captured in
      [TS23.501], a network slice represents a logical network providing
      specific network capabilities and network characteristics. In
      Information Object Class NetworkSliceSubnet [TS28.541 Clause 6.3.2], the
      attribute TransportRef per 3GPP interfaces F1-U and NgU/N3 is used to
      specify a list of EP_Transport Information Object Class (IOC)
      instance(s) associated with these interfaces in per logical link
      fashion.</t>

      <t>Information Object Class EP_Transport [TS28.541 Clause 6.3.18]
      represents logical interface parameters of 3GPP subsystems, providing
      specific network capabilities and network characteristics. Relationships
      of Transport slicing-related 3GPP IOCs and IETF domain represented on
      the Figure X for NgU/N3 slices with traffic between 3GPP CU-UP (or ORAN)
      CU-UP and 3GPP UPF, while the Figure Y similarly represents F1-U slices
      with traffic between 3GPP (or ORAN) DU and 3GPP (or ORAN) CU-UP .</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[                +----------------------------------+
                |      Slices in 3GPP domain       |
                |  Model defined in IOC TS 28.541  |
                |          NgU/N3 slices           |
                +----+--------------------------+--+
   +-----------------|+                         |
   |   3GPP CU-UP /  ||                       +-|---------------+
   | ORAN O-CU-UP #1 ||        .-----.        | |3GPP (i)UPF #1 |
   | +---------------V|      ,'  TN   `.      +-V--------------+|
   | | EP_NgU link to |     |  domain   |     | EP_N3 link to  ||
   | |     UPF #1     |    ;             :    |    CU-UP #1    ||
   | |+---------------|    ;  .-------.  :    +---------------+||
   | ||EP_Transport 10+------(Slice 10 )------|EP_Transport 10|||
   | |+---------------|   |   `-------'   |   +---------------+||
   | |                |   |               |   |                ||
   | |+---------------|   :   .-------.   ;   +----------------||
   | ||EP_Transport 20+------(Slice 20 )------|EP_Transport 20 ||
   | |+---------------|A   :  `-------'  ;   A+----------------||
   | +----------------||    |           |    |+----------------+|
   |            . . . ||     |         |     || . . .           |
   | +----------------||      `.     ,'      |+----------------+|
   | | EP_NgU link to ||        `---'        || EP_NgU link to ||
   | |     UPF #N     ||                     ||   CU-UP #N     ||
   | +----------------||                     |+----------------+|
   +------------------+|                     |+-----------------+
                       |                     |
                +------+---------------------+--------+
                |    logical transport interfaces     |
                |     e.g. GTP-U, IPSec endpoint      |
                +-------------------------------------+

Figure 5-1 Slicing example on the NgU/N3 interface
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t/>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                 +----------------------------------+
                 |      Slices in 3GPP domain       |
                 |  Model defined in IOC TS 28.541  |
                 |            F1-U slices           |
                 +-+-------------------------+------+
    +--------------|+                       +|-----------------+
    |  3GPP DU /   ||                       ||  3GPP CU-UP /   |
    | ORAN O-DU #1 ||                       ||ORAN O-CU-UP #1  |
    |              ||        .-----.        ||                 |
    |+-------------V|      ,'  TN   `.      +V---------------+ |
    || EP_F1-U link |     |  domain   |     |EP_F1-U link to | |
    || to CU-UP #1  |    ;             :    |     DU #1      | |
    |+--------------|    ;   .-----.   :    +--------------+ | |
    ||EP_Transport 1+-------(Slice 1)-------|EP_Transport 1| | |
    |+--------------|   |    `-----'    |   +--------------+ | |
    ||              |   |               |   |                | |
    |+--------------|   :    .-----.    ;   +--------------+ | |
    ||EP_Transport 2+-------(Slice 2)-------|EP_Transport 2| | |
    |+--------------|A   :   `-----'   ;   A+--------------+ | |
    |+--------------||    |           |    |+----------------+ |
    |         . . . ||     |         |     || . . .            |
    |+--------------||      `.     ,'      |+----------------+ |
    || EP_F1-U link ||        `---'        ||EP_F1-U link to | |
    || to CU-UP #N  ||                     ||     DU #N      | |
    |+--------------||                     |+----------------+ |
    +---------------+|                     |+------------------+
                     |                     |
                     |                     |
              +------+---------------------+--------+
              |    logical transport interfaces     |
              |     e.g. GTP-U, IPSec endpoint      |
              +-------------------------------------+
Figure 5-2 Slicing example on the F1-U interface]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>To make slicing a reality, every technical domain is split into one
      or more logical network partitions, each referred to as a network slice
      subnet. The definition of multiple slice subnets on a single domain
      allows each segment to provide differentiated behaviors, in terms of
      functionality and/or performance, tailored to some specific needs. The
      stitching of slice subnets across the RAN, CN and TN results in the
      definition of 5G network slices in 3GPP.</t>

      <t>From a management viewpoint, the concept of network slice subnet
      represents an independently manageable yet composable portion of a
      network slice. The rules for the definition of network slice subnets and
      their composition into network slices are detailed in the 5G Network
      Resource Model (NRM) [TS28.541], specifically in the Network Slice NRM
      fragment. This fragment captures the information model of 5G network
      slicing, which specifies the relationships between different slicing
      related managed entities, each represented as a separate Information
      Object Class (IOC). An IOC captures the semantics and attributes of a
      manageable entity; in other words, it defines the class based on which
      instances (objects) from this entity can be created. In the model, four
      different IOCs are cosnidered:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>NetworkSlice IOC, representing a network slice. This IOC is
          associated with one or more ServiceProfiles, each representing the
          requirements of a particular service. The 1:N relationship of
          NetworkSlice IOC with the ServiceProfile is because one network
          slice can host multiple services, as long as they do not impose
          conflicting requirements.</t>

          <t>NetworkSliceSubnet IOC, associated with a network slice subnet.
          This IOC is associated with one or more SliceProfiles.</t>

          <t>ManagedFunction IOC, which represents a 5G network function.</t>

          <t>EP_Transport IOC, which represents an interface associated with
          transport network level information, e.g., transport address,
          reachability information, and QoS profiles.</t>
        </list>For the transport (i.e., connectivity) related part of a
      network slice, the key focus is on the EP_Transport IOC. Instances of
      this IOC serves to instantiate 3GPP interfaces (e.g., N3) which are
      needed to support Network Slicing and to define Network Slice transport
      resources within the 5G NRM. In a nutshell, the EP_Transport IOC permits
      to define additional logical interfaces for each slice instance of the
      3GPP user plane.</t>

      <t>According to [TS28.541], the EP_Transport construct on 3GPP side has
      the following attributes:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>ipAddress (mandatory): specifies the IP address assigned to the
          logical transport interface. It is used for transport routing.
          Assigned uniquely per slice. As per [TS28.541] IP address is defined
          as an IPv4 address or an IPv6 address. The concern is that for the
          coherent networking, IP address should be assigned to the interface
          with a network mask, to form an IPv4 or IPv6 prefix.</t>

          <t>logicInterfaceInfo (mandatory): a set of parameters, which
          includes logicInterfaceType and logicInterfaceId. It specifies the
          type and identifier of a logical interface. It could be a VLAN ID,
          MPLS Tag or Segment ID. This is assigned uniquely per slice.</t>

          <t>nextHopInfo (optional): identifies the ingress transport node.
          Each node can be identified by any combination of IP address of
          next-hop router of transport network, system name, port name and IP
          management addresses of transport nodes.</t>

          <t>qosProfile (optional): specifies the set of QoS parameters which
          are logically provisioned on both sides on a logical transport
          interface. This is assigned uniquely per slice.</t>

          <t>epApplicationRef (mandatory): specifies the list of application
          endpoints associated with the logical transport interface. A
          multiplicity of them may be assigned per slice. This attribute is
          used to maintain association with corresponding 3GPP logical
          interface (NgU (N3), F1_U), to which EP_Transport is related to.
          Notice that one EP_Transport (representing a logical transport
          interface) can be associated with more than one multiple
          EP_Application (representing an application endpoint of a 3GPP
          managed function), but also the other way around. While the first
          case captures the typical situation, the second case can be used for
          the sake of resilience or load balance in the transport network.</t>
        </list>From the Transport Network domain side, these parameters assist
      on the definition of the CE transport interface configuration and shall
      be taken as an input to the transport service model to create coherent
      Network Slice transport service. Fig. Z illustrates how the EP_Transport
      parameters can relate to the IETF ones for determining the endpoint
      connectivity.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[  +-----------------------+        .-----.        +-----------------+
  |     3GPP CU-UP /      |      ,'  TN   `.      | 3GPP (i)UPF #1  |
  |    ORAN O-CU-UP #1    |     |  domain   |     |                 |
  |+----------------------|  +-----------+   :    +----------------+|
  ||EP_NgU link to UPF #1 |  |   PE 1    |   :    | EP_N3 link to  ||
  ||                      |  |           |    :   |    CU-UP #1    ||
  ||+---------------------|  | .-------. |    |   +---------------+||
  |||  EP_Transport for   +--+(Slice 10 )+----+---| EP_Transport  |||
  |||     S-NSSAI FWA     |  |A`-------' |    ;   +---------------+||
  |||logicInterfaceType = |  +|----------+   ;    +----------------+|
  |||       Vlan ID       |   |:             ;    +-----------------+
  ||| logicInterfaceId =  |   | |           |
  |||      Vlan 200       |   |  |         |
  |||ipAddress = 20.2.2.2 |   |   `.     ,'
  ||+--------------A------|   |     `---'
  |+---------------|------| +-+-------------------+
  +----------------|------+ |   nextHopInfoList   |
                   |        |NextHopInfo = IP/mask|
    +--------------+------+ |       of PE 1       |
    | epApplicationRef =  | | system name = PE 1  |
    |EP_NgU link to UPF#1 | |  port name = Gi1/1  |
    +---------------------+ +---------------------+
Figure 5-3 Example of 3GPP EP_Transport IOC TS28.541 parameters with correlation 
to IETF]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Furthermore, that same parameters should be leveraged for
      constituting the connectivity construct allowing endpoint
      interconnection. That is, there is no additional information that could
      be leveraged at service level that the one provided by EP_Transport,
      which essentially reflects an endpoint view. Fig. W represents this
      relationship between 3GPP and IETF parameters.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   3GPP subsystem - CE                   Transport Network node - PE
 +----------------------+                 +----------------------+
 |InformationObjectClass|                 |   IETF Slice Model   |
 |                      <----------------->                      |
 |     EP_Transport     |                 |  LxSM + extensions   |
 +----------------------+                 +----------------------+

 Representation of connectivity:
 EP_NgU/N3, link between (O)-CU-UP and UPF 
 F1-U, link between (O)-DU and (O)-CU-UP

Figure 5-4 Relationships of the 3GPP parameters with the IETF parameters]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Leveraging on the EP_Transport information, the IETF NSC should be
      instructed through its NBI on performing the slice connection. Fig. Q
      graphically represents the slice connection (e.g., for Ng-U/N3) as
      expected by 3GPP by using connectivity constructs (of a IETF Network
      Slice service) to be configured by the IETF Network Slice
      Controller.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[     Slices in 3GPP domain                         Slices in 3GPP domain
  Model defined in IOC TS 28.541          Model defined in IOC TS 28.541

 +------------------+                                +------------------+
 |3GPP CU-UP / ORAN |                                |   3GPP UPF #1    |
 |   O-CU-UP #1     |      Slices in IETF domain     |                  |
 |                  |                                |                  |
 |+-----------------|     +----+           +----+    +-----------------+|
 || EP_NgU link to  |     |PE 1|           |PE 2|    |  EP_N3 link to  ||
 ||     UPF #1      |     |    |    .-.    |    |    |    CU-UP #1     ||
 ||+----------------|     |    |   |   |   |    |    +----------------+||
 ||| EP_Transport   |     |    |  |     |  |    |    |EP_Transport for|||
 |||for S-NSSAI 100 o--------------PDU 1-------------o  S-NSSAI 100   |||
 |||   Vlan 100     |     |    | |       | |    |    |    Vlan 100    |||
 |||  IP 10.1.1.2   |<--->|    | ;       : |    |<-->|  IP 10.1.1.2   |||
 ||+----------------|     |    |;         :|    |    +----------------+||
 ||+----------------|     |    ||         ||    |    +----------------+||
 ||| EP_Transport   |     |    ||         ||    |    |EP_Transport for|||
 |||for S-NSSAI 200 o--------------PDU 2-------------o  S-NSSAI 200   |||
 |||   Vlan 200     |     |    ||         ||    |    |    Vlan 200    |||
 |||  IP 20.2.2.2   |<--->|    ||   TN    ||    |<-->|  IP 20.2.2.2   |||
 ||+----------------|     |    ||         ||    |    +----------------+||
 ||                 |     |    ||         |+----+    +-----------------+|
 |+-----------------|     |    ||         |          +------------------+
 |+-----------------|     |    |:         ;+----+    +------------------+
 || EP_NgU link to  |     |    | :       ; |PE 3|    |   3GPP UPF #2    |
 ||     UPF #2      |     |    | |       | |    |    +-----------------+|
 ||Serving S-NSSAI  o--------------PDU 3-------------o  EP_N3 link to  ||
 ||      100        |<--->|    |  :     ;  |    |<-->|    CU-UP #1     ||
 |+-----------------|     |    |  :     ;  |    |    | Serving S-NSSAI ||
 +------------------+     +----+   `. ,'   +----+    |       100       ||
                                    '                +-----------------+|
                                                     +------------------+
Figure 5-5 Example of CU-UP Slice in the 3GPP domain using an IETF Network Slice service ]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>According to the [TS28.541] attributes in the EP_Transport, the IETF
      Network Slice may be defined by the following combination of the
      parameters:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   +------------------------------------------------------------------+
   |                   EP_Transport attribute name                    |
   |                                                                  |
   +---------------+----------------+----------------+----------------+
   |   ipAddress   |logicInterfaceId|   nextHopInfo  | qosProfile     |
   +---------------+----------------+----------------+----------------+
   |                   Different                     |  Same for all  |
   |                   per slice                     |    slices      |
   +---------------+---------------------------------+----------------+
   |  Same for all |           Different             |  Same for all  |
   |    slices     |           per slice             |    slices      |
   +---------------+----------------+----------------+----------------+
   |   Different   |  Same for all  |   Different    |  Same for all  |
   |   per slice   |    slices      |   per slice    |    slices      |
   +---------------+----------------+----------------+----------------+
   |         Same for all           |   Different    |  Same for all  |
   |           slices               |   per slice    |    slices      |
   +--------------------------------+----------------+----------------+
   |                            Different                             |
   |                            per slice                             |
   +---------------+--------------------------------------------------+
   |  Same for all |                    Different                     |
   |    slices     |                    per slice                     |
   +---------------+--------------------------------------------------+
     Figure 5-6: EP_Transport parameters map to IETF Slice realizations]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>From the perspective of IETF Network Slice realization, some of these
      options could be realized in a straightforward manner while other could
      require of advanced features (e.g., PBR, SRv6, FlexE, etc).</t>

      <t>IETF Network Slice service may be a set of techniques and underlaying
      technologies, so multiple models may be used to define slice.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="5G E2E Network Slice Mapping Procedure">
      <t>This section provides a general procedure of network slice
      mapping:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                   +-----------------+
                   |       NSMF      |
                   +-----------------+
        +----------|     S-NSSAI     |----------+
        |          |(e.g. 011111111) |          |
        |          +-----------------+          |
        |                   |                   |
        V                   V                   V   
 +-------------+ +---------------------+ +-------------+
 |  RAN NSSMF  | |       IETF NSC      | |   CN NSSMF  |
 +-------------+ +---------------------+ +-------------+
 |   RAN Slice | | IETF Network Slice  | |   CN Slice  |
 | Identifier  | |     Identifier      | |  Identifier |    
 | (e.g., 4)   | |     (e.g., 6)       | |  (e.g., 1)  |    Management
 +-------------+ +---------------------+ +-------------+      Plane
      |           |                   |           |      -----------------
      |           |                   |           |             
      V           V                   V           V      -----------------
      / \      +-----+             +-----+    +-------+        Data
     /RAN\ ----|  PE |-----...-----| PE  |----|  CN   |        Plane
    /-----\    +-----+             +-----+    +-------+


Figure-6 Relation between IETF and 3GPP Network Slice management
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>1. NSMF receives the request from CSMF for allocation of a network
      slice instance with certain characteristics.</t>

      <t>2. Based on the service requirement , NSMF acquires requirements for
      the end-to-end network slice instance , which is defined in Service
      Profile(<xref target="TS28541"/> section 6.3.3).</t>

      <t>3. Based on Service Profile, NSMF identified the network function and
      the required resources in AN, CN and TN networks. It also assigns the
      unique ID S-NSSAI.</t>

      <t>4. NSMF sends a request to AN NSSMF for creation of AN Slice.</t>

      <t>5. NSMF sends a request to CN NSSMF for creation of CN Slice.</t>

      <t>6. NSMF sends a request to IETF Network Slice Controller (NSC) for
      creation of IETF Network Slice. The request contains such attribute such
      as endpoints, required SLA/SLO along with other IETF network slice
      attributes. It also cotains mapping informatin for IETF Network Slice
      Interworking Identifier.</t>

      <t>7. NSC realizes the IETF network slice which satisfies the
      requirement of IETF network slice between the specified endpoints (RAN/
      CN edge nodes). It assigns sliceID and send it to NSMF.</t>

      <t>8. NSMF has the mapping relationship between S-NSSAI and IETF Network
      Slice ID;</t>

      <t>9. When the User Equipment (UE) appears, and during the 5G
      signalling, it requests to be connected to specific e2e network slice
      identified by S-NASSI. Then a GTP tunnel (which is UDP/IP) will be
      created.</t>

      <t>10. UE starts sending traffic in context of e2e network slice for
      specific S-NASSI.</t>

      <t>11. In context of GTP tunnel, the AN edge nodes encapsulates the
      packet with sliceIID according to the selected S-NSSAI ans send it to
      the transport network.</t>

      <t>12. The transport network edge node receives the IP packet and parses
      the sliceIID from the packet and maps the packet to the corresponding
      IETF network slice. It may encapsulate packet with sliceID if needed
      (for example for enforcing QoS in transport network).</t>

      <section title="5G E2E Network Slice Mapping in Management Plane">
        <t>The transport network management Plane maintains the interface
        between NSMF and TN NSSMF, which 1) guarantees that IETF network slice
        could connect the AN and CN with specified characteristics that
        satisfy the requirements of communication; 2) builds up the mapping
        relationship between NSI identifier and TN NSSI identifier; 3)
        maintains the end-to-end slice relevant functions;</t>

        <t>Service Profile defined in<xref target="TS28541"/> represents the
        requirement of end-to-end network slice instance in 5G network.
        Parameters defined in Service Profile include Latency, resource
        sharing level, availability and so on. How to decompose the end-to-end
        requirement to the transport network requirement is one of the key
        issues in Network slice requirement mapping. GSMA(Global System for
        Mobile Communications Association) defines the <xref target="GST"/> to
        indicate the network slice requirement from the view of service
        provider. <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slice-nbi-yang"/>
        analysis the parameters of GST and categorize the parameters into
        three classes, including the attributes with direct impact on the IETF
        network slice definition. It is a good start for selecting the
        transport network relevant parameters in order to define Network Slice
        Profile for Transport Network. Network slice requirement parameters
        are also necessary for the definition of transport network northbound
        interface.</t>

        <t>Inside the TN NSSMF, it is supposed to maintain the attributes of
        the IETF network slice. If the attributes of an existing TN NSSI could
        satisfy the requirement from TN Network Slice Profile, the existing TN
        NSSI could be selected and the mapping is finished If there is no
        existing TN NSSI which could satisfy the requirement, a new TN NSSI is
        supposed to be created by the NSSMF with new attributes.</t>

        <t>TN NSSI resource reservation should be considered to avoid over
        allocation from multiple requests from NSMF (but the detailed
        mechanism should be out of scope in the draft)</t>

        <t>TN NSSMF sends the selected or newly allocated TN NSSI identifier
        to NSMF. The mapping relationship between NSI identifier and TN NSSI
        identifier is maintained in both NSMF and TN NSSMF.</t>

        <t>YANG data model for the Transport Slice NBI, which could be used by
        a higher level system which is the Transport slice consumer of a
        Transport Slice Controller (TSC) to request, configure, and manage the
        components of a transport slices. The northbound Interface of IETF
        network slice refers to <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slice-nbi-yang"/>.</t>

        <t/>

        <t>At the time of provisioning a 3GPP slice, it is required to provide
        slice connectivity constructs by means of IETF network slices. Then it
        is necessary to bind two different endpoints, as depicted in Figure
        2:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Mapping of EP_Transport (as defined by [TS28.541]) to the
            endpoint at the CE side o f the IETF network slice. This is
            necessary because the IETF Network Slice Controller (NSC) will
            receive as input for the IETF network slice service the set of
            endpoints at CE side to be interconnected</t>

            <t>Mapping of the endpoints at both CE and PE side. The endpoint
            at PE side should be elicited by some means by the NSC, in order
            to establish and set up the connectivity construct intended for
            the customer slice request, according to the SLOs and SLEs
            received from the higher level system.</t>
          </list><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
      3GPP concern

      -----------                                            ---------
               /                                            /
              /                                            /
             O EP_Transport_left       EP_Transport_right O
            /A                                           /A
           / |                                          / |
      -----  |                                         ---|-------
             |                                            |
             |                                            |
      .......|............................................|..........
             |                                            |
             |                                            |
             |                                            |
      -------|--       ----------            ----------   |  -------
             | /      /        /  ____      /        /    | /
             V/      /        /  (    )    /        /     V/
             O<---->O        0==(      )==0        O<---->O
            /      /        /    (____)  /        /      /
           /      /        /            /        /      /
      -----      ----------            ----------      ----------
      CE_left     PE_left               PE_right       CE_right

      IETF concern]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t/>

        <section title="Mapping EP_transport to IETF NS CE endpoints">
          <t>The 3GPP Management system provides the EP_Transport IOC to
          extend the slice awareness to the transport network. The
          EP_Transport IOC contains parameters as IP address, additional
          identifiers (i.e., vlan tag, MPLS label, etc), and associated QoS
          profile. This IOC is related to the endpoints of the 3GPP managed
          functions (EP_Application IOC).</t>

          <t>The information captured in the EP_Transport IOC (3GPP concern)
          should be translated into the CE related parameters (IETF concern).
          There will be cases where such translation is straightforward, as
          for instance, when the 3GPP managed functions run on monolithic,
          purpose- specific network elements, in the way that the IP address
          attribute from the EP_Transport IOC is the IP address of an
          interface of the network element. In this case, the information on
          EP_Transport IOC can be directly passed to the IETF NSC through the
          NBI, even though some additional information could be yet required,
          not being defined yet on 3GPP specifications (e.g., the mask
          applicable to the IP address field on EP_Transport).</t>

          <t>However, there could be other cases where such a relationship is
          not straightforward. This could be the case of virtualized 3GPP
          managed functions that could be instantiated on a general-purpose
          network element. In these other cases it is necessary to define
          additional means for eliciting the endpoint at the CE side
          corresponding to the endpoint of the 3GPP-related function.</t>

          <t>With solely EP_Transport characterization in 3GPP, we could
          expect the NS CE endpoint being identified by a combination of IP
          address and some additional information such as vlan tag or SRv6
          label that could discriminate against a certain logical interface.
          The next hop router information is related to the next hop view from
          the perspective of the 3GPP entity part of the slice, then providing
          hints for determining the slice endpoint at the other side of the
          slice service. Finally, the QoS profile helps to determine
          configurations needed at the PE side to respect the SLOs in the
          connection between CEs slice endpoints.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Mapping IETF NS CE to PE endpoints">
          <t>As described in [I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slices], there are
          different potential endpoint positions for an IETF NS.</t>

          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[              |<---------------------- (1) ---------------------->|
              |                                                   |
              | |<-------------------- (2) -------------------->| |
              | |                                               | |
              | |        |<----------- (3) ----------->|        | |
              | |        |                             |        | |
              | |        |  |<-------- (4) -------->|  |        | |
              | |        |  |                       |  |        | |
              V V   AC   V  V                       V  V   AC   V V
          +-----+   |    +-----+                 +-----+    |   +-----+
          |     |--------|     |                 |     |--------|     |
          | CE1 |   |    | PE1 |. . . . . . . . .| PE2 |    |   | CE2 |
          |     |--------|     |                 |     |--------|     |
          +-----+   |    +-----+                 +-----+    |   +-----+
             ^              ^                       ^              ^
             |              |                       |              |
             |              |                       |              |
          Customer       Provider                Provider       Customer
          Edge 1         Edge 1                  Edge 2         Edge 2


                  Figure 7: IETF Network Slice endpoints]]></artwork>
            </figure>The information that is passed to the IETF NSC in terms
          of endpoints is the information relative to the CE position, which
          is the one known by the slice customer. From that information, the
          NSC needs to infer the corresponding endpoint position at PE side,
          in order to setup the desired connectivity constructs with the SLOs
          indicated in the request.</t>

          <t>Being slice request technology-agnostic, the identification of
          the slice endpoints at the PE side should leverage on generic
          information passed through the NBI to the IETF NSC.</t>

          <t/>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="5G E2E Network Slice Mapping in Control Plane">
        <t>There is no explicit interaction between transport network and
        AN/CN in the control plane, but the S-NSSAI defined in <xref
        target="TS23501"/> is treated as the end-to-end network slice
        identifier in the control plane of AN and CN, which is used in UE
        registration and PDU session setup. In this draft, we assume that
        there is mapping relationship between S-NSSAI and NSI in the
        management plane, thus it could be mapped to a IETF network slice
        .</t>

        <t>Editor's note: The mapping relationship between NSI defined in
        <xref target="TS23501"/> and S-NSSAI defined in <xref
        target="TS23501"/> is still in discussion.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="5G E2E Network Slice Mapping in Data Plane">
        <t>If multiple network slices are carried through one physical
        interface between AN/CN and TN, IETF Network Slice Interworking ID in
        the data plane needs to be introduced. If different network slices are
        transported through different physical interfaces, Network Slices
        could be distinguished by the interface directly. Thus IETF Network
        Slice Interworking ID is not the only option for network slice
        mapping, while it may help in introducing new network slices.</t>

        <section title="Data Plane Mapping Considerations">
          <t>The mapping relationship between AN or CN network slice
          identifier (either S-NSSAI in control plane or NSI/NSSI in
          management plane) and IETF Network Slice Interworking ID needs to be
          maintained in AN/CN network nodes, and the mapping relationship
          between IETF Network Slice Interworking ID and IETF Network Slice is
          maintained in the edge node of transport network. When the packet of
          a uplink flow goes from AN to TN, the packet is encapsulated based
          on the IETF Network Slice Interworking ID; then the encapsulation of
          IETF Network Slice Interworking ID is read by the edge node of
          transport network, which maps the packet to the corresponding IETF
          network slice.</t>

          <t>Editor's Note: We have considered to add "Network Instance"
          defined in [TS23501]in the draft. However, after the discussion with
          3GPP people, we think the concept of "network instance" is a
          'neither Necessary nor Sufficient Condition' for network slice.
          Network Instance could be determined by S-NSSAI, it could also
          depends on other information; Network slice could also be allocated
          without network instance (in my understanding) And, IETF Network
          Slice Interworking ID is not a competitive concept with network
          instance.IETF Network Slice Interworking ID is a concept for the
          data plane interconnection with transport network, network instance
          may be used by AN and CN nodes to associate a network slice with
          IETF Network Slice Interworking ID</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Data Plane Mapping Options">
          <t>The following picture shows the end-to-end network slice in data
          plane:</t>

          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[+--+       +-----+                           +----------------+
|UE|- - - -|(R)AN|---------------------------|       UPF      |
+--+       +-----+                           +----------------+
 |<----AN NS---->|<----------TN NS---------->|<----CN NS----->|     

]]></artwork>
            </figure>The mapping between 3GPP slice and transport slice in
          user plane could happens in:</t>

          <t>(R)AN: User data goes from (radio) access network to transport
          network</t>

          <t>UPF: User data goes from core network functions to transport
          network</t>

          <t>Editor's Note: As figure 4.7.1. in <xref target="TS28530"/>
          describes, TN NS will not only exist between AN and CN but may also
          within AN NS and CN NS. However, here we just show the TN between AN
          and CN as an example to avoid unncessary complexity.</t>

          <t>The following picture shows the user plane protocol stack in
          end-to-end 5G system.<figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[+-----------+                    |                  |               |
|Application+--------------------|------------------|---------------|
+-----------+                    |                  | +-----------+ |
| PDU Layer +--------------------|------------------|-| PDU Layer | |
+-----------+   +-------------+  |  +-------------+ | +-----------+ |
|           |   | ___Relay___ |--|--| ___Relay___ |-|-|           | |
|           |   |     \/ GTP-U|--|--|GTP-U\/ GTP-U|-|-|   GTP-U   | |
|   5G-AN   |   |5G-AN +------+  |  +------+------+ | +-----------+ |
|  Protocol |   |Protoc|UDP/IP|--|--|UDP/IP|UDP/IP|-|-|   UDP/IP  | |
|   Layers  |   |Layers+------+  |  +------+------+ | +-----------+ |
|           |   |      |  L2  |--|--|  L2  |  L2  |-|-|     L2    | |
|           |   |      +------+  |  +------+------+ | +-----------+ |
|           |   |      |  L1  |--|--|  L1  |  L1  |-|-|     L1    | |
+-----------+   +-------------+  |  +-------------+ | +-----------+ |
     UE              5G-AN       |        UPF       |      UPF      |
                                 N3                 N9              N6
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The following figure shows the typical encapsulation in N3
          interface which could be used to carry the IETF Network Slice
          Interworking ID between AN/CN and TN.</t>

          <t><figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[+------------------------+
| Application Protocols  |     
+------------------------+      
|       IP (User)        |  
+------------------------+     
|          GTP           |    
+------------------------+      
|          UDP           |         
+------------------------+
|          IP            |
+------------------------+
|       Ethernet         |
+------------------------+
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <section title="Layer 3 and Layer 2 Encapsulations">
            <t>If the encapsulation above IP layer is not visible to Transport
            Network, it is not able to be used for network slice interworking
            with transport network. In this case, IP header and Ethernet
            header could be considered to provide information of network slice
            interworking from AN or CN to TN.</t>

            <t><figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[+------------------------+-----------
| Application Protocols  |      ^
+------------------------+      |
|       IP (User)        |  Invisible
+------------------------+     for
|          GTP           |     TN
+------------------------+      |
|          UDP           |      V     
+------------------------+------------
|          IP            |
+------------------------+
|       Ethernet         |
+------------------------+]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>

            <t>The following field in IP header and Ethernet header could be
            considered :</t>

            <t>IP Header:</t>

            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>DSCP: It is traditionally used for the mapping of QoS
                identifier between AN/CN and TN network. Although some values
                (e.g. The unassigned code points) may be borrowed for the
                network slice interworking, it may cause confusion between QoS
                mapping and network slicing mapping.;</t>

                <t>Destination Address: It is possible to allocate different
                IP addresses for entities in different network slice, then the
                destination IP address could be used as the network slice
                interworking identifier. However, it brings additional
                requirement to IP address planning. In addition, in some cases
                some AN or CN network slices may use duplicated IP
                addresses.</t>

                <t>Option fields/headers: It requires that both AN and CN
                nodes can support the encapsulation and decapsulation of the
                options.</t>
              </list>Ethernet header</t>

            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>VLAN ID: It is widely used for the interconnection between
                AN/CN nodes and the edge nodes of transport network for the
                access to different VPNs. One possible problem is that the
                number of VLAN ID can be supported by AN nodes is typically
                limited, which effects the number of IETF network slices a AN
                node can attach to. Another problem is the total amount of
                VLAN ID (4K) may not provide a comparable space as the network
                slice identifiers of mobile networks.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Two or more options described above may also be used together
            as the IETF Network Slice Interworking ID, while it would make the
            mapping relationship more complex to maintain.</t>

            <t>In some other case, when AN or CN could support more layer 3
            encapsulations, more options are available as follows:</t>

            <t>If the AN or CN could support MPLS, the protocol stack could be
            as follows: <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[+------------------------+-----------
| Application Protocols  |      ^
+------------------------+      |
|       IP (User)        |  Invisible
+------------------------+     for
|          GTP           |     TN
+------------------------+      |
|          UDP           |      V     
+------------------------+------------
|         MPLS           |
+------------------------+
|          IP            |
+------------------------+
|       Ethernet         |
+------------------------+]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>

            <t>A specified MPLS label could be used to as a IETF Network Slice
            Interworking ID.</t>

            <t>If the AN or CN could support SRv6, the protocol stack is as
            follows:</t>

            <figure>
              <artwork><![CDATA[+------------------------+-----------
| Application Protocols  |      ^
+------------------------+      |
|       IP (User)        |  Invisible
+------------------------+     for
|          GTP           |     TN
+------------------------+      |
|          UDP           |      V     
+------------------------+------------
|          SRH           |
+------------------------+
|         IPv6           |
+------------------------+
|       Ethernet         |
+------------------------+]]></artwork>
            </figure>

            <t>The following field could be considered to identify a network
            slice:</t>

            <t>SRH:</t>

            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>SRv6 functions: AN/CN is supposed to support the new
                function extension of SRv6.</t>

                <t>Optional TLV: AN/CN is supposed to support the extension of
                optional TLV of SRH.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Above Layer 3 Encapsulations">
            <t>If the encapsulation above IP layer is visible to Transport
            Network, it is able to be used to identify a network slice. In
            this case, UPD and GTP-U could be considered to provide
            information of network slice interworking between AN or CN and
            TN.</t>

            <t><figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[+------------------------+----------
| Application Protocols  |     |
+------------------------+ Invisible  
|       IP (User)        |     for
+------------------------+     TN
|          GTP           |     | 
+------------------------+------------        
|          UDP           |          
+------------------------+
|          IP            |
+------------------------+
|       Ethernet         |
+------------------------+]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>

            <t>The following field in UDP header could be considered:</t>

            <t>UDP Header:</t>

            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>UDP Source port: The UDP source port is sometimes used for
                load balancing. Using it for network slice mapping would
                require to disable the load-balancing behavior.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Example of IETF Network Slice request through IETF Network Slice NBI">
      <t>As discussed in <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slices"/>,
      to fulfill IETF network slices and to perform monitoring on them, an
      entity called IETF Network Slice Controller (NSC) is required to take
      abstract requests for IETF network slices and realize them using
      suitable underlying technologies. An IETF Network Slice Controller is
      the key building block for control and management of the IETF network
      slice. It provides the creation/modification/deletion, monitoring and
      optimization of transport Slices in a multi-domain, a multi- technology
      and multi-vendor environment.</t>

      <t>Figure 8 shows the NSC and its NBI interface for 5G. Draft <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slice-nbi-yang"/> a addresses the
      service yang model of the NSC NBI interface for all network slicing
      use-cases.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[               +------------------------------------------+
               |            5G Customer (Tenant)          |
               +------------------------------------------+
                                  A
                                  |
                                  V
               +------------------------------------------+
               |    5G E2E Network Slice Orchestrator     |
               +------------------------------------------+
                                  A
                                  | NSC NBI
                                  V
               +------------------------------------------+
               |    IETF Network Slice Controller (NSC)   |
               +------------------------------------------+
                                  A
                                  | NSC SBI
                                  V
               +------------------------------------------+
               |          Network Controller(s)           |
               +------------------------------------------+

               Figure 8: IETF Network Slice Controller NBI for 5G]]></artwork>
        </figure>As discussed in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slices"/>, the main task of the IETF
      Network Slice Controller is to map abstract IETF network slice
      requirements from NBI to concrete technologies on SBI and establish the
      required connectivity, and ensure that required resources are allocated
      to IETF network slice. There are a number of different technologies that
      can be used on SBI including physical connections, MPLS, TSN, Flex-E,
      PON etc. If the undelay technology is IP/MPLS/Optics, any IETF models
      can be used during the realization of IETF network slice.</t>

      <t>There are no specific mapping requirements for 5G. The only
      difference is that in case of 5G, the NBI interface contains additional
      5G specific attributes such as customer name, mobile service type, 5G
      E2E network slice ID (i.e. S-NSSAI) and so on (See Section 6). These 5G
      specific attributes can be employed by IETF Network Slice Controller
      during the realization of 5G IETF network slices on how to map NBI to
      SBI. They can also be used for assurance of 5G IETF network slices.
      Figure 9 shows the mapping between NBI to SBI for 5G IETF network
      slices.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[                        | (1) NBI: Request to create/modify/delete
                         |          5G IETF Network Slice
                         V
             +----------------------+
             |  IETF Network Slice  | (2) Mapping between technology
             |    Controller (NSC)  |     agnostics NBI to technology
             +----------------------+     specific SBI
                       ^ ^ ^
                       | | |
                   |---| | |---|  (3) SBI: Realize 5G IETF Network Slice
                   |     |     |      by using various IETF models for
                   V     V     V      services, tunnels and paths
             +----------------------+
             |       Network        |-+
             |     Controller(s)    | |-+
             +----------------------+ | |
               +----------------------+ |
                 +----------------------+


     Figure 9: Relationship between transport slice interface and IETF
                     Service/Tunnels/Path data models]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section title="Gap Analysis">
      <t>The way in which 3GPP is characterizing the slice endpoint (i.e.,
      EP_Transport) is based on Layer 3 information (e.g., the IP Address).
      However the information provided seems not to be sufficient for
      instructing the IETF Network Slice Controller for the realization of the
      IETF NEtwork Slice. For instance, some basic information such as the
      mask associated to the IP address of the EP_Transport is not specified,
      as well as other kind of parameters like the connection MTU or the
      connectivity type (unicast, multicast, etc). More sophisticated
      information could be required as well, like the level of isolation or
      protection necessary for the intended slice.</t>

      <t>In the case in which the 3GPP managed function runs on a purpose-
      specific network element, the IP address specified in the EP_Transport
      IOC serves as reference to identify the CE endpoint, assuming the
      endpoint of the CE has been configured with that IP address. With that
      information (together with the logical interface ID) should be
      sufficient for the IETF NSC to identify the counterpart endpoint at the
      PE side, and configuring it accordingly (e.g., with a compatible IP
      address) for setting up the slice end-to-end. Similarly, the next hop
      information in EP_Transport can help validate the end-to-end slice
      between PE endpoints.</t>

      <t>In the case in which the 3GPP managed function is instantiated as a
      virtualized network function, the direct association between the IP
      address of EP_Transport and the actual endpoint mapped at the CE is not
      so clear. It could be the case, for instance when the virtualized
      network function is instantiated at the internal of a data center, that
      the CE facing the PE is far from the point where the function is
      deployed, being that connectivity extended through the internals of the
      data center (or by some internal configuration of a virtual switch in a
      server). In these situations additional information is needed for
      accomplishing the end-to-end connection.</t>

      <t>At the same time, [TS28.541] IOC contains useful parameters to be
      used in IETF Network Slice creation mechanism and enreaching IETF
      Network Slice model. The following parameters may be suggested as a
      candidates to the correlation of the IETF Network Slice parameters and
      IETF Network Slice model enreachments:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>For the latency, dLThptPerSliceSubnet, uLThptPerSliceSubnet,
          reliability and delayTolerance attributes, the following NRM apply
          (with reference to the section in that specification):</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>CNSliceSubnetProfile (section 6.3.22 in [TS28.541])</t>

              <t>RANSliceSubnetProfile (section 6.3.23 in [TS28.541])</t>

              <t>TopSliceSubnetProfile (section 6.3.24 in [TS28.541])</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>For the qosProfile attribute, the NRM which applies is
          EP_Transport (detailed in section 6.3.17 in [TS28.541])</t>
        </list></t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t/>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The work of Luis M. Contreras has been partially funded by the
      European Commission under Horizon 2020 project Int5Gent (grant agreement
      957403)</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>Jose Ordonez-Lucena</t>

      <t>Telefonica</t>

      <t>Ronda de la Comunicacion,</t>

      <t>s/n Sur-3 building,</t>

      <t>3rd floor Madrid 28050 Spain</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: joseantonio.ordonezlucena@telefonica.com</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Ran Pang</t>

      <t>China Unicom</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: pangran@chinaunicom.cn</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Liuyan Han</t>

      <t>China Mobile</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: hanliuyan@chinamobile.com</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Jaehwan Jin</t>

      <t>LG U+</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: daenamu1@lguplus.co.kr</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Jeff Tantsura</t>

      <t>Microsoft</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: jefftant.ietf@gmail.com</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Shunsuke Homma</t>

      <t>NTT 3-9-11,</t>

      <t>Midori-cho Musashino-shi,</t>

      <t>Tokyo 180-8585 Japan</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: shunsuke.homma.ietf@gmail.com</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Xavier de Foy</t>

      <t>InterDigital Inc.</t>

      <t>Canada</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: Xavier.Defoy@InterDigital.com</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Philip Eardley</t>

      <t>BT</t>

      <t>UK</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: philip.eardley@bt.com</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Kiran Makhijani</t>

      <t>Futurewei Networks</t>

      <t>US</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: kiranm@futurewei.com</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Hannu Flinck</t>

      <t>Nokia</t>

      <t>Finland</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: hannu.flinck@nokia-bell-labs.com</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Rainer Schatzmayr</t>

      <t>Deutsche Telekom</t>

      <t>Germany</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: rainer.schatzmayr@telekom.de</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Ali Tizghadam</t>

      <t>TELUS Communications Inc</t>

      <t>Canada</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: ali.tizghadam@telus.com</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Christopher Janz</t>

      <t>Huawei Canada</t>

      <t>Canada</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: christopher.janz@huawei.com</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Henry Yu</t>

      <t>Huawei Canada</t>

      <t>Canada</t>

      <t/>

      <t>Email: henry.yu1@huawei.com</t>

      <t/>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slice-definition'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slices'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slice-nbi-yang'?>

      <reference anchor="ZSM003"
                 target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3144">
        <front>
          <title>ETSI ZSM003</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year=""/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS23501"
                 target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3144">
        <front>
          <title>3GPP TS23.501</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year=""/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS28530"
                 target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/               SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3273">
        <front>
          <title>3GPP TS28.530</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year=""/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS28531"
                 target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3274">
        <front>
          <title>3GPP TS28.531</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year=""/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS28541"
                 target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=3400">
        <front>
          <title>3GPP TS 28.541</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year=""/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="GST"
                 target="https://www.gsma.com/newsroom/all-documents/generic-network-slice-template-v2-0/">
        <front>
          <title>Generic Network Slice Template</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year=""/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="InfRef">
        <front>
          <title/>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2004"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="An Appendix">
      <t/>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
